Link, Eugene P.; Papers apap025
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
- Professional Correspondence, 1933-1993; 2; 1 cubic foot
  - Union Theological Seminary Alumni, 1981-1989 (Box 3 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 7)
  - Unitarian-Universalist Fellowship, 1965-1992 (Box 3 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 8)
  - United States-China Peoples Friendship Association, 1976-1977 (Box 3 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 9)
  - Vermont, University of, 1969-1982 (Box 3 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 10)
  - "Women on War", 1939 (Box 3 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 11)
    [correspondence with Beulah Link].
  - Wullschegler, Gerret [former pastor of Links], Undated (Box 3 (2-Professional Correspondence), Folder 11)
- Labor Activities, 1966-1992; 3; 0.2 cubic ft.
  Link first joined the American Federation of Teachers (AFT) in 1935 while he was teaching history at Mt. Hermon School for Boys in Northfield, Massachusetts. At that time, Link's principal concern was to resist the signing of a teachers' oath and Governor [of Massachusetts] James M. Curley's attacks on the freedom of speech and the academic exchange of ideas. Link became a founding member of the United University Professions (UUP) and attempted to establish teachers unions wherever he taught in the 1930s-1950s (South Carolina, New Jersey, and Colorado). Link's work in the AFT and UUP is illustrated by this series (although only since the year 1966). Especially noted is his role as Vice President of the State University Federation of Teachers in the early 1970s; his leadership in the area of Membership Development for the UUP (even after retirement from active teaching in 1977, Link travelled around the country helping to organize higher education unions on seven other campuses while offering advice to organizers on countless others); his inspiration in the creation of the Council of Active Retired Members (CO-ARM); and his support of union activities in many fields throughout the world.
  Link's unflinching support of unionism has brought him several awards. In 1985, he was recognized for his fiftieth year of involvement in the AFT. At the same time, Link helped initiate the scholarship for service-minded students which bear his name. Five years later (1990), he received the prestigious Diamond Service Award from the AFT. All of these events are chronicled in this series.
  Finally, it should be mentioned that the commitment to unionism brought a good deal of opposition into the lives of Link and others of similar minds. Two early significant grievance cases against the administration of the State University of New York System, those of William Bruce and George Cranford, are examined in this series. In both cases, Link played the role of unofficial advisor to the aggrieved parties rather than active participant.
  - American Federation of Teachers/United University Professions, 1966-1972 (Box 3 (3-Labor Activities), Folder 12)
  - American Federation of Teachers/United University Professions, 1973-1992 (Box 3 (3-Labor Activities), Folder 13)
  - Bruce, William, Case, 1972-1974 (Box 3 (3-Labor Activities), Folder 14)
  - Central Labor Coalition of Clinton, Essex, and Warren Counties, Correspondence [Link organizer and vice president], 1974 (Box 3 (3-Labor Activities), Folder 15)
  - Council of Active Retired Members (CO-ARM), United University Professions, 1982-1992; 2 folders (Box 3 (3-Labor Activities), Folder 16-17)
  - Cranford, George, and AFT Case, 1971 (Box 3 (3-Labor Activities), Folder 18)
  - Diamond Service Award [AFT], Eugene Link, 1990 (Box 3 (3-Labor Activities), Folder 19)
  - Farm Workers Project, Unitarian-Universalist Church Board, Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Box 3 (3-Labor Activities), Folder 20)
  - Fiftieth Year in AFT/UUP, Recognition of Eugene Link, 1985-1988 (Box 3 (3-Labor Activities), Folder 21)
  - Link, Eugene P., United University Professions Scholarship, 1987-1996 (Box 3 (3-Labor Activities), Folder 22)
  - Oral History Project, United University Professions, Transcript, 1990-1992 (Box 3 (3-Labor Activities), Folder 23)
  - Solidarity Committee, United University Professions, 1992 (Box 3 (3-Labor Activities), Folder 24)
- Teaching Career, 1933-1977; 1985; 4; 0.8 cubic ft.
  Despite his multifold interests, Link was first and foremost a teacher of social history. His long teaching career, which spanned nearly five decades, is illuminated by two subseries dealing with institutional correspondence and lecture notes.
  Link taught as a full-time, permanent faculty member at seven schools in Massachusetts, South Carolina, New Jersey, Colorado, and New York. In addition, he was twice a Fulbright Lecturer in India and a one-year visiting professor in Britain and the Peoples Republic of China. Link's institutional correspondence covers all variety of educational matters, great and small, in which he was involved. In this subseries, particular attention is given to Link's career at the State University of New York, Plattsburgh (1963-77). The folder detailing this tenure contains Link's correspondence with George Angell (president of Plattsburgh, SUNY, from 1954-74). Link had known Angell when both served at the State University College of New Paltz, New York (Link as the Chair of the Social Science Division, 1950-63; Angell the Dean of the College, 1949-53). It was largely this friendship that led Link to Plattsburgh as "research professor" in 1963.
  The second major subseries deals with Link's lecture notes from twenty courses taught at New Paltz, Plattsburgh, and Hull, England, over thirty-two years. Due to his interests in Third World cultures and minority rights in America, Link successfully introduced several courses in the 1970s that dealt with American cultural and social history including: African American, women's, Indian, and Asian studies. In that sense, he was a pioneer of the modern emphasis on multiculturalism in the State of New York University System.
  - Subseries 1: Institutional Correspondence, 1933-1989; 4.1
    - Annamalai University [India] (Fulbright Lectures), 1955 (Box 3 (4-Teaching Career), Folder 25)
    - Limestone College, Gaffney, S.C., 1938-1940 (Box 3 (4-Teaching Career), Folder 26)
    - Mt. Hermon School [Mass.], 1933-1937 (Box 3 (4-Teaching Career), Folder 27)
    - New Jersey State Teachers College, 1944-1947 (Box 3 (4-Teaching Career), Folder 28)
    - State University of New York, New Paltz, 1950-1963 (Box 3 (4-Teaching Career), Folder 29)
    - State University of New York, Plattsburgh, 1958-1989 (Box 3 (4-Teaching Career), Folder 30)
      Including George Angell correspondence.
    - University of Denver [with photos], 1946-1951 (Box 3 (4-Teaching Career), Folder 31)
    - Winthrop [S.C.] State Women's College, 1942-1944 (Box 3 (4-Teaching Career), Folder 32)
  - Subseries 2: Lecture Notes, 1953-1985; 4.2
    - New Paltz, Undated; 4.2.1
      - "American History, Readings In" (SS-518), 1953 (Box 3 (4.2.1-New Paltz), Folder 33)
      - "American People, Social and Cultural History of the" (HIS-203/204), 1958-1959 (Box 3 (4.2.1-New Paltz), Folder 34)
    - Plattsburgh, Undated; 4.2.2
      - "Afro-American, Social History of the" (HIS-205), 1970 (Box 3 (4.2.2-Plattsburgh), Folder 35)
      - "American History, Twentieth Century" (HIS-402/406), 1965-1967 (Box 3 (4.2.2-Plattsburgh), Folder 36)
      - "American Labor, History of" (HIS-304), 1974-1977 (Box 3 (4.2.2-Plattsburgh), Folder 37)
      - "American Labor Movement, Recent Trends in the [Seminar]" (HIS-509), 1976 (Box 4 (4.2.2-Plattsburgh), Folder 1)
      - "American Peace Movements" (HIS-515), 1973 (Box 4 (4.2.2-Plattsburgh), Folder 2)
      - "Asian Seminar" (HIS-552s), Plattsburgh, 1966 (Box 4 (4.2.2-Plattsburgh), Folder 3)
      - "Black History, Seminar" (HIS-501), 1969-1971 (Box 4 (4.2.2-Plattsburgh), Folder 4)
      - "Historiography" (HIS-370 [later 380]), 1968; 1977 (Box 4 (4.2.2-Plattsburgh), Folder 5)
      - "India, History of" (HIS 253s), 1965-1976 (Box 4 (4.2.2-Plattsburgh), Folder 6)
      - "Revolutionary Movements, Modern" (HIS-357), 1964 (Box 4 (4.2.2-Plattsburgh), Folder 7)
      - "Senior Seminar" (HIS-400), Plattsburgh, 1969-1970 (Box 4 (4.2.2-Plattsburgh), Folder 8)
      - "United States, Social and Cultural History of the" (HIS-301), 1964-1973 (Box 4 (4.2.2-Plattsburgh), Folder 9)
      - "United States, Social and Cultural History of the" (HIS-302), 1970 (Box 4 (4.2.2-Plattsburgh), Folder 10)
      - "United States Civilization" (HIS-101), 1965-1973 (Box 4 (4.2.2-Plattsburgh), Folder 11)
      - "United States Civilization" (HIS-102), 1977; 1985 (Box 4 (4.2.2-Plattsburgh), Folder 12)
      - "United States Social and Cultural History" (HIS-430), 1964-1966 (Box 4 (4.2.2-Plattsburgh), Folder 13)
      - "Women in America, Seminar" (HIS-480), 1974 (Box 4 (4.2.2-Plattsburgh), Folder 14)
      - "Women in the U.S., History of" (HIS-303/305), 1971-1975 (Box 4 (4.2.2-Plattsburgh), Folder 15)
      - "Women's Rights in America, History" [readings; supplement to HIS-480], early 1970s (Box 4 (4.2.2-Plattsburgh), Folder 16)
      - Hull, England [Visiting Professorship, 1975] (Box 4 (4.2.2-Plattsburgh), Folder 17)
    - Notes For Various Courses, Undated (Box 4 (4-Teaching Career), Folder 18)
- Writings By Eugene P. Link, 1940-1992; 5; 0.8 cubic ft.
  This series is divided into four subseries: (1) articles (organized by decade); (2) published manuscripts; (3) unpublished manuscripts; and (4) correspondence.
  The first subseries contains copies of most of the nearly forty articles produced by Link over the course of fifty years. Although almost all of the articles fit into the category of American social history, many deal with Link's particular interest: the social ethics of American and Canadian physicians. Consequently, the subjects of Link's articles are often socially active and humanitarian minded physicians like Abraham and Mary Jacobi, the Barton brothers, Jonathan Knight, Elizabeth Blackwell, Harvey Cushing, the Mayo Family, and Norman Bethune.
  The second subseries contains the texts of six manuscripts that were published from 1940-90. Once again, the major theme of the humanitarian impulse within the American medical profession is most prominent.
  The third subseries deals with unpublished manuscripts. Two of these are concerned with marriage and the family (a popular interest of both Dr. and Mrs. Link in the late 1940s and early 1950s). Various miscellaneous writings of Link (poems, funeral eulogies, etc.) can be found in this subseries as well.
  The final subseries contains the lengthy correspondence that Link produced in his effort to get his writings published. Although this correspondence largely parallels and elaborates the subseries on articles and published manuscripts, two folders relate specifically to Link's communications with various individuals in the American medical profession and provide insight into how Link gathered research material on some of his most significant writings.
  - Subseries 1: Articles, 1941-1990; 5.1
    - Link, Eugene, 1941-1950 (Box 4 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 19)
    - Link, Eugene, 1951-1960 (Box 4 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 20)
    - Link, Eugene, 1961-1970 (Box 4 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 21)
    - Link, Eugene, 1971-1980 (Box 4 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 22)
    - Link, Eugene, 1981-1990; Undated (Box 4 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 23)
  - Subseries 2: Published Manuscripts, 1940-1990; 5.2
    - "Franklin's Friend [David] Hartley: English Poor Richard" [text, research notes, and photos], 1975-1976 (Box 4 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 24)
    - The Humanitarian Trend in American Medicine, The Social Ideas of Physicians by Link, 1990 (Box 4 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 25)
    - McGraw-Hill Encyclopedia of World Biography, Link's Contributions To, 1969 (Box 4 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 26)
    - "The Psychosomatic Outlook of Drs. Abraham and Mary Putnam Jacobi", by Link, 1952 (Box 4 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 27)
    - Teachers's Handbooks For ERPI Classroom Films Inc. [Link collaborator; 7 pamphlets], 1943 (Box 4 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 28)
    - Victories in the Villages by Link, 1964; 1979 (Box 4 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 29)
  - Subseries 3: Unpublished Manuscripts, 1949-1951; 5.3
    - "Marriage and the Family", ca. 1949 (Box 4 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 30)
    - Miscellaneous and Unpublished Writings by Link, Undated (Box 4 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 31)
    - "Notes on the European Study Tour on Marriage and Family Life Led By Dr. Eugene P. Link" [by Dorothy C. Houts], 1951 Summer (Box 4 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 32)
  - Subseries 4: Correspondence, 1940-1992; 5.4
    - Beaumont, William, Link's Correspondence Relating To, 1985-1992 (Box 5 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 1)
    - Bethune, Norman, Link's Correspondence Concerning His Book On [with slides], 1974-1992 (Box 5 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 2)
    - Blackwell Family Correspondence, 1947 (Box 5 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 3)
    - Democratic-Republican Societies by Link [publ. of], 1941-1985 (Box 5 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 4)
    - Jacobis Article Correspondence by Link, 1943-1953 (Box 5 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 5)
    - Medical Profession Correspondence, 1949-1977; 2 folders (Box 5 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 6-7)
    - "The Psychosomatic Outlook of Drs. Abraham and Mary Putnam Jacobi", Link's Correspondence Relating To, 1940-1951 (Box 5 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 8)
    - The Social Ideas of Physicians by Link, Publication Correspondence, 1984-1992 (Box 5 (5-Writings By Eugene P. Link), Folder 9)
- Publications by other Authors, 1891-1989; 6; 0.7 cubic ft.
  In this series are publications (mostly journal articles) of interest to Link that were produced by other authors. In a certain sense, they can be categorized as specific and non-specific (although they are not divided into actual subseries).
  Roughly forty percent of this series deals with publications whose authors are specifically noted by Link. Perhaps most prominently are those professional publications produced by Link's children (Martha Casey, Perry and Bruce Link; as well as Martha's husband, Charles Casey, a professor of Chemistry at the University of Wisconsin at Madison). Other specific writings are from Cyril Bibby, a noted Huxley scholar; Caldwell Esselstyn, a medical doctor known for his emphasis on holistic healing; and John Ise, an economics professor from the University of Kansas, who was "blacklisted" by many professional economic associations for his socialist leanings.
  The remainder of the series tends to be unspecific with regard to the authors of the articles saved by Link. The implication is that Link saved these writings, not because he knew or admired their authors, rather, he saved them because their subjects caught his interest. Hence, these articles reflect many of Link's concerns: labor issues, humanitarianism and the medical profession, Marxism and Communism, the U.S. involvement in Nicaragua, propaganda, and trilateralism. In addition, this series is a bit of a catch-all category, containing travel pamphlets that Link collected during his Hull Lectureship in 1975.
  - "Aesthetics and Criticism", 1953-1954 (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 10)
  - Bibby, Cyril, 1960s (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 11)
  - Broadside, The [protest publication], 1963 (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 12)
  - Colleagues, Miscellaneous, 1946-1987 (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 13)
  - Cooperatives, Articles On, 1930s-1960s (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 14)
  - Esselstyn, Caldwell B. M.D., 1953-1962 (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 15)
  - Friedrich, Ernst, Guerre a la Guerre [with annotations by Link], 1928 (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 16)
  - Hull Lectureship, Pamphlets Collected During, 1975 (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 17)
  - International Physicians For the Prevention of Nuclear War and Physicians For Social Responsibility, Information On, 1987 (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 18)
  - Ise, John [University of Kansas economics professor], Undated (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 19)
  - Labor, Miscellaneous Essays, 1933-1971 (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 20)
  - Labor Issues [pamphlets], 1891-1982 (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 21)
  - Link Children [Martha Casey, Perry Link, Bruce Link], 1972-1989 (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 22)
  - Marxism and Communism, Various Essays, Undated (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 23)
  - Miscellaneous Interest Articles, Undated (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 24)
  - National Anthem Musical Score Collection, 1964-1966 (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 25)
  - Nicaragua [U.S. involvement in], Essays, 1980s (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 26)
  - Peace Research Papers of the American Historical Association, 1967-1974 (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 27)
  - Propaganda Articles, 1942-1945 (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 28)
  - Trilateralism Articles, 1970s (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 29)
  - USSR Trip Pamphlets, 1975 (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 30)
  - White, William Allen, Articles Relating To, 1963-1985 (Box 5 (6-Publications by other Authors), Folder 31)
- Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward, 1923-1992; 7; 1.2 cubic ft.
  This is one of the most voluminous and significant series in the Link Papers. Harry F. Ward (1873-1966) was an ordained minister in the Methodist Episcopal Church; professor of Christian ethics at Union Theological Seminary from 1918-41 (and emeritus after 1941 until his death in 1966); a founder of the Methodist Federation of Social Service in 1907; and chair of the American Civil Liberties Union from 1920-40. Deeply influenced by the Social Gospel of Washington Gladden and Walter Rauschenbusch, Ward, in turn, impressed the credo of social justice upon hundreds of his student ministers at Union Theological Seminary. Link was one of these students. After serving as Ward's graduate student assistant in the early 1930s, Link followed his theological mentor in the direction of extreme social activism. The large series of Ward materials acquired by Link throughout most of his adult life is testimony to the substantial impact that Ward had upon a more youthful Link.
  The bulk of this series is concerned with Link's book, Labor-Religion Prophet: The Times and Life of Harry F. Ward (Boulder, Colorado: Westview Press, 1984). A book that took many years for Link to write, it is both the chronicle of a little understood, although much admired man, and the tribute of an adoring student for his venerable mentor. Extremely heavy on research materials, the series contains Link's notes, correspondence with Ward, efforts (unsuccessful and successful) to get his book published, and various reviews of the finished work.
  Several folders of materials are concerned with the ninetieth birthday celebration organized for Ward by his admirers in New York City in 1963. Included are correspondence, financial accounts, and two reel-to-reel sound tapes that include the reminiscences of Ruth Crawford Francis, Stephen Fitchman, D.N. Pritt, and other colleagues of Ward.
  Three works of Ward are preserved in this series in manuscript form: The Need For Free Exercise of Religion (1961); "Does This Nation Want the Bill of Rights or the Police State?" (transcript of a speech given by Ward in 1963); and Marx and Jesus (undated, a work that so thoroughly contrasted Marx with Jesus that Ward was unable to find a publisher for it). Of some interest to researchers might be the copy of the FBI file on Ward obtained by the Methodist Federation of Social Action in the 1970s.
  Two folders of Ward materials deal with the family of Harry Ward. In the course of his research, Link became good friends with Ward's wife, Daisy, and three children, Gordon, Lynd, and Muriel. One folder contains this extensive correspondence between Link and the Ward family. The other folder relates specifically to the artwork and woodcarvings of Lynd Ward. A renowned artisan whose subjects often dealt with heroic, labor themes, Lynd Ward gave several woodcarvings to the Link family which were eventually exhibited and donated to the Rockwell Kent Gallery in Plattsburgh in 1986.
  - Contemporaries of Ward, Articles and Essays, 1975-1980 (Box 6 (7-Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward), Folder 1)
  - "Does This Nation Want the Bill of Rights or the Police State?" [Speech by Ward], 1963 (Box 6 (7-Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward), Folder 2)
  - Estey, Ken, "The Pragmatic method in the Writings of Harry F. Ward" [unpublished research paper with Link's annotations], 1992 (Box 6 (7-Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward), Folder 3)
  - France, Ruth C. [Ward's secretary] to Ward, 1960 (Box 6 (7-Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward), Folder 4)
    [includes photo].
  - "Marx and Jesus", Unpublished Manuscript by Ward, Undated (Box 6 (7-Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward), Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence Regarding Link's Book on Ward, 1968-1986 (Box 6 (7-Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward), Folder 6)
  - The Need For Free Exercise of Religion, Manuscript by Ward, 1961 (Box 6 (7-Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward), Folder 7)
  - Religious Activities of Ward [incl. FBI file on Ward], 1920-1960 (Box 6 (7-Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward), Folder 8)
  - Ward, Harry F., Children's Correspondence [sons Lynd and Gordon and their families], 1969-1987 (Box 6 (7-Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward), Folder 9)
  - Ward, Harry F. and Daisy, Correspondence, 1923-1980 (Box 6 (7-Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward), Folder 10)
    [includes letters to Link].
  - Ward, Harry F., Photographs, mostly early 1960s (Box 6 (7-Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward), Folder 11)
  - Ward, Lynd, Donation and Exhibition of His Woodcarvings, 1986-1987 (Box 6 (7-Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward), Folder 12)
  - Ward Book Bibliography and Supporting Materials, 1984 (Box 6 (7-Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward), Folder 13)
  - Ward Book Notes, Undated; 6 folders (Box 6 (7-Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward), Folder 14-19)
  - Ward Book Publisher Correspondence, 1980-1984 (Box 6 (7-Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward), Folder 20)
  - Ward Book Reviews, 1984-1986 (Box 6 (7-Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward), Folder 21)
  - Ward-George Coe Correspondence, ca. 1933 (Box 6 (7-Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward), Folder 22)
  - Ward's 90th Birthday Celebration, Correspondence, 1963 (Box 7 (7-Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward), Folder 1)
  - Ward's 90th Birthday Celebration, Financial Accounts, 1963 (Box 7 (7-Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward), Folder 2)
  - Ward's 90th Birthday Celebration, Sound Recordings, 1963; 2 Reels (Box 7 (7-Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward))
  - Westview Press/Publication of Ward Book, 1982-1986 (Box 7 (7-Materials Relating to Harry F. Ward), Folder 3)
- Materials Relating to the Religious Freedom Committee (RFC), 1954-1964; 8; 0.5 cubic ft.